在上一次讲座中，我们考虑了独立的联合控制，这是一种理想化的
In the last lecture, we considered independent joint control, which is an idealisation of
现实中。通过独立的联合控制，电机扭矩有两个组成部分。它
the real world. With independent joint control, the motor torque has got two components. It
由于电机的惯性，它有一个元件，它有一个由电机引起的元件
has a component due to the motor's inertia, and it has a component due to the motor's
粘性摩擦。因此，一个是电机惯量和电机加速度的函数，
viscous friction. So, one is a function of the motor inertia and the motor's acceleration,
电机的粘性摩擦力和电机的角速度。
the motor's viscous friction and the motor's angular velocity.
现在，我们将考虑更加现实的非独立联合控制案例
Now, we're going to consider the more realistic case of non-independent joint control and
我们在这里添加了所谓的刚体动态术语。这意味着扭矩
we've added the so-called rigid body dynamic terms here. What this means is the torque
在关节J上看到的电动机将受到所有加速度的影响
seen by the motor on joint J is going to be influenced by the acceleration of all
关节，所有关节的速度和重力。现在，我已经介绍过了
of the joints, the velocity of all of the joints, and gravity. Now, I've introduced
这里还有一点额外的表示法。这是下标j，这意味着第j个
a bit of additional notation here. It's the subscript j and what that means is the jth
相应矩阵的行。所以，这是矩阵M的第j行，第j行
row of the corresponding matrix. So, this is the jth row of the matrix M, jth row of
向量G的矩阵C或第j个元素。例如，如果我乘以第j行
the matrix C or the jth element of the vector G. For example, if I multiply the jth row
矩阵M的列向量，即所有关节的加速度，
of the matrix M by the column vector, which is the acceleration of all of the joints,
结果将是一个标量。这是一个标量表达式，因为它是关于扭矩作用的
the result will be a scalar. This is a scalar expression because it's about the torque acting
关于J.你会看到这里有两个术语
on joint J. You'll see that there are two terms here that
涉及联合加速。所以，我要做的是考虑两个组件中的向量Mj。
involve joint acceleration. So, what I'm going to do is consider the vector Mj in two components.
有一个与关节J相关的组件，并且有与之关联的组件
There is the component associated with joint J and there's the component associated with
所有其他关节，我用M吧表示。我可以做一些重新排列
all of the other joints, which I've denoted by M bar. I can do a little bit of rearrangement
现在。我们现在所拥有的是关于作用在关节J上的扭矩的表达式
now. What we have now is an expression for the torque acting on joint J in terms of the
电动机自身的惯性和与该关节相关的惯性矩阵的分量，
motor's own inertia and the component of the inertia matrix associated with this joint,
粘性摩擦，然后，我们在最后的所有其他术语是
the viscous friction, and then, we have all of the other terms at the end which are the
干扰扭矩。这个术语是电机的惯性
disturbance torque. This term here is the inertia of a motor
它是驱动关节J.这是一个可变惯性项，我们从机械手中拔出
which is driving joint J. This is a variable inertia term that we pull out off the manipulator
惯性矩阵。我们有电机接头摩擦，这是电机驱动的功能
inertia matrix. We have the motor joint friction, which is a function just of the motor driving
联合，然后我们有这个相当复杂的干扰术语，这是
the joint, and then we have this rather complex disturbance term on the end, which is the
加速所有其他关节，科里奥利和向心项以及引力
acceleration of all the other joints, the Coriolis and centripetal terms and the gravity
术语。我可以进一步简化它，我们现在有一个新的惯性，我称之为Jprime，
term. I can simplify it even further and we now have a new inertia, I call that J prime,
这是机器人配置的一个功能。它是Q的函数。我们有
which is a function of the configuration of the robot. It's a function of Q. We have our
粘性摩擦和我们有tauD，这是一个集中的扰动扭矩
viscous friction and we have tau D which is the disturbance torque lumped into a single
变量。那么，由此产生的问题是什么？
variable. So, what are the issues that arise from this?
首先，我们有一个问题，因为关节经历的惯性随着变化而变化
Well firstly, we have an issue because the inertia experienced by the joint varies with
机器人的配置。在上一课中，我们调整了控制器
the configuration of the robot. In the last lecture, we tuned our controller so that it
在稳定时间和过冲方面有很好的反应，但调整是一个功能
had a nice response in terms of settling time and overshoot, but the tuning was a function
惯性和粘性摩擦的特定值。现在，我们所说的是
of the particular values of inertia and viscous friction. Now, what we're saying is that the
联合控制器看到的惯性是配置的函数。这取决于
inertia that the joint controller sees is a function of the configuration. It depends
在所有的关节角度。因此，这意味着控制系统的响应将会
on all of the joint angles. So, that means that the response of the control system will
取决于机器人的姿势。
depend on the robot's pose.
另一个大问题是扰动扭矩，这是施加在关节J上的扭矩
The other big issue is the disturbance torque, that's a torque that’s exerted on joint J due
所有其他关节的运动，加速度和速度，以及由于重力。这个
to motion of all the other joints, acceleration and velocity and also, due to gravity. This
可能导致关节的不良运动。它可能会导致路径跟踪错误
may lead to undesirable motion of the joint. It may lead to path following errors, for
例。那么，我们可以对这些问题做些什么呢？嗯，真的很简单
example. So, what can we do about these issues? Well, a really simple technique is really
在机器人中广泛使用的是引入变速箱。大多数机器人都有减速箱。所以，
widely used in robots is to introduce a gearbox. Most robots have a reduction gearbox. So,
输出轴比输入轴旋转G倍。G是装备
the output shaft rotates a factor of G times slower than the input shaft. G is the gear
比。通常发生这种情况的原因是电动机能够运转
ratio. The reason that this typically happens is that electric motors are capable of running
非常非常快，能够达到非常非常高的旋转速度，但通常非常
very, very quickly, capable of very, very high rotational velocity, but generally quite
扭矩低。变速箱的作用是什么，它允许我们权衡一些这种高角度
low in torque. What a gearbox does is it allows us to trade off some of this high angular
电机转矩的速度。扭矩实际上比速度更有用。我们在这里可以看到
velocity for motor torque. Torque is actually more useful than speed. We can see here the
指示齿轮箱输出侧的扭矩和速度之间的关系
relationship between torque and velocity on the output side of the gear box indicated
由下标l。L表示负载侧和输入侧的扭矩和速度
by the subscript l. L meaning the load side and torque and velocity on the input side
由下标m表示。如果我们现在解决我们的表达方式
denoted by the subscript m. If we now address the expression that we had
从上一张幻灯片和介绍变速箱，我们看到表达现在看起来有点
from the previous slide and introduce the gearbox, we see the expression now looks something
像这样。我们可以看到这种变量惯性的影响，惯性就是一种功能
like this. We can see that the effect of this variable inertia, the inertia that's a function
Q，现在正在减少G平方因子。如果我考虑过我的情况
of Q, is now being reduced by a factor of G squared. If I considered the case where I've got
减速箱，其中G等于50，这减少了2500.这是一个非常的，
a reduction gearbox, where G is equal to 50, this is a reduction by 2500. It's a very,
这种配置依赖惯性的非常显着的减少。这意味着电机的
very significant reduction in this configuration dependent inertia. It means that the motor’s
自己的惯性，这个术语在这里将占主导地位。惯性看起来会更加稳定。我们可以
own inertia, this term here, will dominate. The inertia will look more constant. We can
还看到我们的干扰项已减少了G倍。再次，如果我有
also see that our disturbance term has been reduced by a factor of G. Again, if I have
减速比为50，这个术语的重要性比它低50倍
a reduction ratio of 50, this term here is 50 times less significant than it would be
没有变速箱。因此，由于许多原因，变速箱很有用，而且非常有效
without a gearbox. So, a gearbox is useful for many reasons and it's a really effective
减少扰动转矩和配置依赖惯性的影响的方法。
way of reducing the effect of disturbance torques and configuration dependent inertia.
处理这种情况的更复杂的技术是计算这种干扰扭矩。
A more sophisticated technique to deal with this is to compute this disturbance torque.
如果我们有一个动态的机器人模型，我们知道位置，速度和加速度
If we have a dynamic model of our robot and we know the position, velocity and acceleration
在所有链接中，我们可以计算这个扰动项。所以，控制就是
of all of the links, then we can compute this disturbance term. So, the control that is
这里显示的是一个P，D控制器。这是P术语。这是D术语，和
shown here is effectively a P, D controller. This is the P term. This is the D term, and
这是前馈术语，前馈，我们可以计算的干扰。当然，
this is the feedforward term, with the feedforward, the disturbance that we can compute. Of course,
这意味着我们需要准确了解机器人手臂的动态参数。
this means that we need to know accurately the dynamic parameters of our robot arm.
我们可以使用的第三种方法称为计算-扭矩控制。它有一些相似之处
The third approach that we can use is called computed-torque control. It has some similarities
而且，前馈控制表达的一些重要差异。在这里，我们可以
but also, some important differences to the feedforward control expression. Here, we can
看一个有效比例控制器的术语。在这里，我们可以看到一个术语
see a term which is effectively a proportional controller. Here, we can see a term which
实际上是一个衍生控制器。它们乘以惯性矩阵，在这里，
is effectively a derivative controller. They're multiplied by the inertia matrix and here,
我们有向心和科里奥利项和重力项。
we have the centripetal and Coriolis term and the gravity term.
这些不同技术的优点和缺点是什么？变速箱既便宜又简单。
What are the pros and cons of these different techniques? A gearbox is cheap and straightforward.
很多时候，我们总是在机器人中使用变速箱，这样我们就可以使用更便宜的低扭矩电机。
Often times, we use a gearbox in a robot anyway so that we can use a cheaper low torque motor.
变速箱确实增加了成本，增加了重量。它们效率低下而且会产生噪音。
Gearboxes do add cost and they add weight. They do some inefficiency and they make noise.
必须计算每个样品的计算扭矩控制。那么，如果我们的机器人控制器
Computed-torque control has to be computed every single sample. So, if our robot controller
正在运行，比如说，一千赫兹，然后是我们之前的表达
is running, at say, a thousand Hertz, then the expression that we had on the previous
幻灯片需要在一千赫兹计算。这涉及到那些的计算
slide needs to be computed at one thousand Hertz. That involves the computation of those
矩阵，M，C和G矩阵以及一些矩阵乘法。所以很多计算
matrices, the M, the C and the G matrix and some matrix multiplication. So a lot of computation
需要做。曾几何时，这真的非常难以做到。在早些时候
needs to be done. Once upon a time, this was really, really hard to do. In the early days
机器人技术，当计算机真的很慢时，这是一件非常困难的事情。各种各样的
of robotics, when computers were really slow, it was a very hard thing. So, all sorts of
引入了近似值，但今天在频率上非常非常容易地做到这一点
approximations were introduced, but today it's very, very easy to do that at a frequency
像一千赫兹。实际上可以计算前馈控制
like one thousand Hertz. The feedforward control can actually be computed
速度缓慢，这反映了动态扭矩实际上没有变化的现实
at a slow rate, and that reflects the reality that the dynamic torques don't actually change
从一个样本时间到下一个样本时间。因此，前馈控制信号可以
all that much from one sample time to the next. So, the feedforward control signal can
在实现主要控制时，可以计算大约五十赫兹或一百赫兹
be computed at perhaps fifty Hertz or a hundred Hertz, while the main control is implemented
就像一千赫兹。它们不必以相同的速率计算。
at something like one thousand Hertz. They don't have to be computed at the same rate.
对于计算转矩控制和前馈控制，存在重要意义
For the computed-torque control and for the feedforward control, there is a significant
知道每个链接的动态参数的实际值的挑战。
challenge in knowing the actual values of the dynamic parameters of each of the links.
对于每个链接，我们前面讨论过有十个动态参数。所以，对于六个链接
For each link, there are ten dynamic parameters as we discussed earlier. So, for a six link
工业机器人，需要确定60个动态参数。你可以通过实验来做
industrial robot, that's sixty dynamic parameters need to be identified. You can do it experimentally
或者你也许可以从机器人的CAD模型中做到这一点。
or you can perhaps do it from a CAD model of the robot.